This is the Buick Riviera,
the world's first car with a
touchscreen. Made back in 1986,
the futuristic graphic control center
replaced more than 80 physical controls.
The graphics were so advanced, the fan
icon spun at different speeds depending
on the climate control setting. You
could turn the sound system up or down
and adjust the balance or graphic
equalizer. Trip data had its own screen.
There were even electronic gauges.
>> Touch a new [music] Buick Riviera and it
touches you.
>> The Riviera was way ahead of its time,
maybe too far ahead. The influential Car
and Driver magazine gave it a brutal
review. The touchscreen is meant to
transform a trip to the 7-Eleven into a
space odyssey, but the reality of the
graphic control center is a bad joke. It
was fiddly, distracting, and way slower
than the physical controls it replaced.
Customers, it seems, just weren't buying
it. Production numbers plummeted. Three
years later, the touchscreen was removed
from the Riviera.
But the idea wouldn't stay dead.
Ultimately, touchscreens and cars made a
return. This time, they were accompanied
by lots of other features that
supposedly [music] reinvent driving.
High-tech handles that are hard to find
and fiddly to use and all but useless in
cold weather. Gear shifters that are
straight out of Star Wars, but come with
a 4-minute explanation video. Many new
models have been stripped of their
buttons, levers, and knobs. They depend
on software updates as much as they do
solid engineering. There's evidence that
some of these cars aren't just harder to
use, they're less safe. And your car
might be one of them.
>> Confirmed.
>> And I'm like, I want to return off
regenerative braking cuz you used to be
able to well maybe not turn it off, but
you used to be able to reduce it. and
that feature went away. And so I'm I'm
going down these steep mountain roads on
icy conditions with the car trying to
regenerative brake every time I let off
the throttle and I'm like I turn this
thing off and it wasn't there. Even in
the moment trying to find where in the
menu it had gone while you're driving in
the snowstorm on a on a road behind a
transport truck and it's a scary
situation to be hunting a menu in the
middle of winter.
>> In this video we'll explore some of the
dumbest features in modern cars. what it
really means that they're packed with
sensors and why certain design elements
are downright dangerous. Let's start
with the new, the funny, and the just
plain weird.
The marriage of cars and cuttingedge
tech is nothing new.
Entertainment systems and cars have been
constantly advancing since the 1930s. In
every era, automakers have embraced the
entertainment tech of their time. AM
radio, FM radio, tape players, CD
players, even record players. But
sometime in the early 2000s, the insides
of cars started to change in bold new
ways.
And in 2012, one particular car changed
everything.
This is the Tesla Model S. Upon release,
it was considered a huge leap forward
for electric cars. Car and Driver
praised its range, acceleration, and top
speed. Unusually, the Model S was
designed almost entirely around a huge
17-in touchscreen, about as big as four
to six of the touchscreens typically
found in cars at the time. It was a
sensation. I think it did drive the the
revolution to electric cars. It made
people think it was possible, you know?
I mean, no one ever thought it was
possible really to to have electric car
[music] before that came onto the
market.
>> Tesla jump started a craze for
minimalist digital oriented designs in
cars. Beyond enthusiasm, touchscreens
are also cheaper and more efficient to
manufacture than physical controls. And
as of 2018, all new cars sold in the US
were required to have a rear-facing
camera, enabling a driver to detect
pedestrians behind their vehicle. This
meant new cars had to have a screen
inside them. Some experts see a direct
link to the rise of touchscreens.
Whatever the reasons, the Model S and
Tesla Silicon Valley software first
approach felt unique. The company
unveiled new cars like Apple presented
new iPhones. Even if Tesla wasn't the
first company to include a touchcreen in
a car, for many people, the future
finally seemed to have arrived.
Suddenly, the rest of the industry was
playing catch-up. To avoid being left
behind, companies would have to shift
gears. Unfortunately, along with a lot
of other things, shifting was about to
get really, really confusing.
Congratulations. This is your new 2017
Range Rover VR. You're going to love
driving it.
But first, you need to get inside.
But how? Where are the There have to be
handles. How else? Maybe they're No.
Okay. No. Are they No. Higher. Higher.
Look, you just need a little finesse.
First, press this little button. Then
the handle pops out. It's not that hard.
But you might have to explain the
procedure to your passengers
and things could get tricky in the
winter. Okay, this will probably take
some getting used to, but they're so
sophisticated.
The Veilar is just the tip of the
iceberg. [music] These days, lots of
cars have unusual door handles. Some,
like the Ford Mustang Mache, got rid of
handles entirely. Instead, there's a
button and they've camouflaged it. The
Tesla Cybert trucks button is even
better hidden. But back to your new
Veilar. Inside, you'll notice more
oddities. Here's the shifter. As usual,
the gears are labeled, but instead of
the classic levershaped shifter, you use
a dial to change gears. The 2017
Mercedes-Benz GLC has a monostable stock
shifter. It's always returned to the
center, which can make it tough to tell
which gear you were currently in. The
GMC Terrain moves shifting to buttons,
which you pull rather than push. In its
review, the website Motor 1 called it a
complicated solution to a non-existent
problem. A description that may or may
not apply to many of the innovations in
this video. From 2021 to 2023, if you
were driving a Volkswagen ID4, you
shifted gears with this thing. See it
there? Hidden behind the steering wheel.
You twist it to shift gears. Whether
these new designs actually improve on
anything is an open question, but they
certainly bring the adventure back to
driving. In the past, most cars
essential controls tended to look and
feel more or less the same. With new
features like these, every time you
drive a different car, you have to learn
how to operate it almost from scratch,
but there's confusing. And then there's
the Genesis Crystal Sphere.
Let's say you ease on into a Genesis
EV60.
You want to back out of your parking
spot. Wait, there's no shifter, just
this little crystal ball. According to
Genesis, it helps create an emotional
connection between the driver and the
vehicle. So, slow down. Take a minute.
Can you feel it?
You start the car by pressing the brake
[music] and pressing this button. Like
magic, the crystal sphere rotates,
revealing the shift dial. Inside,
there's a mood light. Shift into reverse
by twisting the dial to the [music]
left. The dial vibrates, but nothing's
wrong. No, that's the sweet vibration of
safety. The mood light changes color,
too, putting you in a safety mood.
You can't feel it. Okay, you know what?
Let's take a step back. Try putting the
car in neutral. With it still turned
off, press the start button twice, but
don't hold down the brake pedal. No,
don't hold down the brake. Okay, try
again. Without holding down the brake
pedal, [music] press the start button
twice. Good. Now you're in IGN mode.
Remove the cap next to the crystal
sphere.
Well, there should be a cap there. Okay,
skip the cap. Press that button. The one
next to the crystal sphere. Good. Good.
Now you're in neutral. The touchcreen
tells you so. The sphere rotates.
There's the shift dial so you can Oh,
but you're already in neutral. Why would
You know what? Never mind. If you don't
get it, you're clearly not alone.
Genesis created a nearly 4-minute video
to explain how to use the crystal
sphere. Of course, [music] cars have had
weird shifters before, but these days it
seems to be the shifter wild west. By
2017, things had gotten so crazy, Car
and Driver published an article, "Why
are so many new cars gear selectors so
stupid?" And naturally, it doesn't end
there. According to Wired, 97% of new
cars released after 2023 have at least
one screen inside them. And some
physical controls for many essential
functions have disappeared entirely. In
the past, you typically open a glove
compartment by pulling a handle. These
days, if you own a Tesla, you well, you
have to use the touchcreen.
>> Well, you got to go, you know, sort of
there's a little car button and it
brings up a menu and then it's I think
it's usually the default the top top
menu thing has these grid of various
buttons and things you can do and then
you go to the glove box and then that'll
open the glove box and then you can
actually you can enter a security code
if you if you want. Then you have to hit
the fourdigit pin to unlock the glove
box, but you still have to close the
glove compartment manually.
As modern cars become increasingly tech-
based, some manufacturers have explored
treating them more like software by
selling upgrades or subscriptions. In
2022, BMW announced that certain
features of its cars would be available
only by subscription. To use their cars
heated seats, for example, British
customers had to pay £15 a month. By
late 2023, BMW had dropped the idea due
to low customer interest. A much better
deal is a subscription to Brilliant, the
online platform for really learning
about serious topics in math, science,
programming, and more. Brilliant isn't
just more userfriendly than your 500
browser tabs full of random tutorials.
It's way more effective. Brilliant
courses are designed by teachers,
researchers, and professionals from
places like MIT, Stanford, and Google.
So, even heady courses like digital
circuits, programming with Python, and
abstract thinking are about more than
rope memorization. Instead, Brilliant
lets you get hands-on with concepts and
play around with them, a method that is
proven to be six times more effective
than watching lecture videos. You can
use Brilliant on your computer or your
phone, so you can always get a quick hit
of knowledge even when you're on the go.
To learn for free on Brilliant, go to
brilliant.org/fern. Scan the QR code on
screen or click the link in the
description. Brilliant's also given our
viewers 20% off an annual premium
subscription, which gives you unlimited
daily access to everything on Brilliant.
In many ways, modern cars have come to
feel like smartphones on wheels. They're
packed with infotainment options, but
hidden inside them is a major downside
most drivers aren't aware of.
Many modern cars have advanced features
that rely on huge amounts of data from
the surrounding environment.
>> Your car is a kind of data hoover,
really hoovering up everything. And what
you'd hope is that data is being used to
improve things all the time.
>> This is Professor Dale Harrow. He's
chair of the intelligent mobility design
center and head of the intelligent
mobility design program at the Royal
College of Art in London.
>> You know, I know Tesla do a lot of this
where they're looking at kind of how
people use the car and all that data
about road conditions, road surfaces.
So, you could have a car that's talking
to another car that says, "I've just
gone over a terrible pothole." The car
behind says, "Oh, no. I'm coming up to
it now. I'll avoid that." You know, so
it could be very good all this sort of
stuff. But some cars don't just collect
data about driving conditions. They
collect data about you, how you move,
your speech, even your facial
expressions. Back in 2023, the Mosilla
Foundation, a pro privacy tech focused
nonprofit, researched 25 different car
brands to examine their approach to
driver data and privacy in the US. Of
the 25 brands, the foundation concluded
that pretty much all of them collected
more data than necessary to make their
products work smoothly. And in their
privacy agreements, most brands reserve
the right to share drivers personal data
and sell it.
According to Mozilla, that data went way
beyond name, address, and phone number.
It could also include your age,
birthday, and the location of your
phone. your credit card number and
information about how you financed and
bought your car, products or services
you've bought, products or services
you've considered buying, your ID
number, your social security number,
your passport number, health status,
signature, the shape of your face,
fingerprints, [music] your gate, genetic
characteristics, race, religion and
philosophical beliefs, employment
information, whether you belong to a
union, nationality, immigration status,
[music] photos, location history,
recordings of your voice and the
gestures you make. And at least two
companies, Nissan and Kia, explicitly
claim the right to collect information
about customers sex lives.
>> [music]
>> We don't know whether companies do
collect all this information, but in
their privacy policies, the automakers
Mosilla studied reserve the right to do
so. There's also no way of knowing
exactly how your car might collect data
about your life. But a look around a
modern car suggests some ways that it
could. First, there's your phone. If you
connect it to your car, either over
Bluetooth or by plugging it in, you're
potentially offering up an enormous
treasure trove of data. Some cars store
your contact list. Some keep a log of
your phone calls. Then there's the
cameras and sensors that make many of
the driver assist features in modern
cars possible, including automatic lane
centering, adaptive cruise control, and
partial self-driving. Like many cars,
the Tesla Model Y uses cameras and
sensors to gather real-time data from in
and around the car surroundings. Here's
one camera mounted above the rear
license plate. Here are two more, one in
each door pillar. There are three in the
windshield right above the rearview
mirror and one in each front fender.
Depending on your model, there's also
one inside the car right above the
rearview mirror. Tesla says its cameras
are designed from the ground up to
protect your privacy. But in 2023, nine
former Tesla employees told Reuters
[music] that images and video taken from
customers cars have been repeatedly
shared around the Tesla office between
2019 and 2022.
These reportedly included mundane images
employees turned into intra office
memes, video of road rage incidents and
crashes, including one of a Tesla
hitting a child on a bike, and footage
that was clearly private and even
embarrassing. Apparently, including a
man approaching the car, totally naked.
According to one ex employee, some of
these recordings seem to have been made
by cars that weren't even turned on,
showing off whatever weird stuff
customers happen to have in their
garages. [music] According to Reuters,
several years ago, Tesla employees
stumbled upon footage of Wet Nelly, the
submersible vehicle from the James Bond
movie, The Spy Who Loved Me, dry docked
in a Tesla owner's garage. In this case,
the owner was Elon Musk. He may or may
not have been aware his collectible was
being recorded.
According to Reuters, Tesla collected
video recordings from vehicles that were
turned off only with the owner's
consent, but has long since stopped
doing so. And Tesla does let drivers opt
out of their vehicle collecting data,
but there's a cost. This might lead to
quote reduced functionality, serious
damage, or inoperability.
Oh, and Nissan's privacy policy makes
you promise to inform any passengers
about the features and limitations of
your car system and services, including
Nissan's data collection terms. Pinky
Swear'll do it, and be sure to print out
the whole policy for the next time you
give a friend a lift. None of the car
companies Mosilla dealt with would
disclose exactly who they share driver
data with. And some policies are very
broad. Your data could be used for
marketing purposes or an insurance
company could raise your rates based on
data about you driving. And without you
ever knowing, your most sensitive
information could be shared with the
government or law enforcement. Hyundai's
policy specifies that it will comply
with lawful requests, whether formal or
informal. These practices vary according
to region. In the United States, for
example, they seem to essentially be
legal. In Europe, the law requires that
companies offer specific justifications
for processing consumers data, but the
effectiveness of those laws relies on
compliance. Evidence suggests that
companies still collect huge amounts of
driver data, and that data may not
always be securely stored. In the end,
Mosilla came to the conclusion that of
all the tech they ever reviewed, cars
were the worst data collectors. [music]
We never had a category where we
couldn't find something good that we
could recommend to somebody to choose
over something bad. [music]
>> And since the study was published, it's
not clear much has changed. But it isn't
just about your car and who knows who
else knowing your sexual preferences.
Some modern features are just plain
dangerous.
This is Quakala Mountain Pass near
Vancouver, Canada. And this is Quinn
Duffy. He owns a 2022 Tesla Model Y,
which he drives over the pass on trips
to the interior of British Columbia. He
told us about his experiences.
>> It's a high mountain pass. uh frequently
has terrible weather, fog, heavy snow.
>> These situations need your full
attention. But in snowy conditions, the
Model Y's automatic high beams can blind
the driver. And turning them off while
driving can be a nightmare.
>> And they Yeah, the automatic headlights
keep coming on. They'll disable when
they sense a car in front. So on
occasion, they would they would shut off
if we were coming up behind a big truck
or something. But you have to go into,
you know, this big screen. You have to
go into car functions. You have to go
into headlights or lighting. you have to
try and find the high beams or the
automatic headlights to try and disable
these things. And I'm trying to get my
wife beside me to, you know, I'm trying
to to talk her through this the screens
to find these options because I'm trying
to concentrate on driving while while
being blinded by by these high beams in
in heavy snow and fog. If I'm trying to
do that myself, it's a screen. There's
no physical button. There's no muscle
memory. There's no haptic feedback. So,
you're trying to watch the options on a
low contrast screen that you can't touch
cuz the car is bumpy and your finger's
bouncing around. These buttons are
small. Like, there's a lot of of really
frustrating design features when they're
trying to pack so much software and so
much control into a screen into multiple
menus. You know, I I think it's a it's
potentially dangerous, right?
>> Duffy is a game designer and he's no
stranger to technology and even
automative professionals have struggled
with the innovations in new cars.
In 2024, Kelly Funkhouser took the
Rivian S1, an electric SUV, out for a
[music] test drive. When traffic started
to slow, she checked that adaptive
cruise control, which automatically
keeps the car a certain distance from
any vehicles in front of it, was turned
off. That required quickly flicking the
shifter next to the steering wheel
upward. But Funkhouser held that gesture
slightly too long, a couple of seconds.
Suddenly, the SUV shifted into reverse
and began backing up towards the
vehicles behind her.
Kelly Funkhouser is the associate
director of vehicle technology at
Consumer Reports, and she test drives
cars for a living. Yet, even she
couldn't avoid the usability hiccups
that come with rapidly changing car
design. Luckily, Funkhouser's experience
was just a near miss. In June 2016, the
actor Anton Yelchin, who played Mr.
Czechov in the 2009 film reboot of Star
Trek, parked his Jeep Grand Cherokee on
a steep hill outside his home in Studio
City, California. The Jeep was one of
1.1 million vehicles that FIA Chrysler
had recalled months before. This was due
to the monostable shifter, which always
returned to the center position. That
could make it difficult to tell what
gear was selected. As Yelchin walked
towards his home, the Jeep rolled
backwards and hit him, crushing him
against a brick pillar and security
fence. There's no proof that the Jeep's
monostable shifter was responsible for
Yelchin's death. While his parents filed
a wrongful death case against Fiat
Chrysler, it was later settled out of
court. [music] But a week later, the
National Highway Traffic Safety
Administration concluded its
investigation into the shifters, and it
seemed to reveal a worrying pattern. 686
complaints, 266 crashes or fires, and 68
associated injuries. Since the early
'7s, the general trend in the US has
been a decline in motor vehicle deaths.
But around 2011, they began climbing
again. In 2023 alone, there were 45,000
motor vehicle deaths. That's roughly the
population of an entire town. Professor
David Straer of the University of Utah,
who has studied infotainment systems and
driver distraction, said this.
>> Something's going on that's actually
making our roads less safe. And it
corresponds with increased prevalence of
cell phones and touch screens and all
electronics in the vehicle.
>> In 2020, the British road safety charity
IM Roads Smart commissioned a study on
the impact of Apple CarPlay on driver
reaction times. On a close course, two
groups of 20 drivers were asked to
perform touchscreen tasks while driving.
One group used Apple CarPlay, the other
one Android Auto. It found that while
using either voice or touch controls,
drivers had a much harder time staying
in their lane and maintaining a
consistent distance from vehicles in
front of them. When something appeared
on the road ahead, they reacted over 50%
more slowly than usual. When drivers
selected music on Spotify using touch
controls, their reaction times were even
worse than in previous studies of
texting while driving. Ultimately,
compared to previous studies conducted
by TLR, using either system slow drivers
reaction times more than being at the
legal limit for alcohol or cannabis.
In 2022, a Swedish car magazine compared
11 new touchscreen equipped cars to a
17-year-old Volvo with old school
physical controls. While driving 110
kmh, drivers performed simple tasks like
adjusting climate control or changing
the radio station. The outcome was
unambiguous. Drivers performed the task
far faster using physical controls. It
took them just 10 seconds, and during
that time, the car traveled 306 m. At
the other end of the spectrum, using the
touchscreen controls took 44.6 6 seconds
in the worst performing car. During that
time, it traveled 1,372 m. In other
words, the driver was distracted by the
touchcreen for almost a mile. The weird
door handles in modern cars may also be
a safety concern.
>> And you have an accident, for example,
and and the firemen or the policemen
come by and they have to get you out of
the car. There's nothing to grab. You
know, how are you going to open the car?
You have to bust the glass and all that.
This is Frank Stephenson, chief creative
officer at Frank Stefins Design and one
of the most influential living car
designers.
>> Typically, door handles were also used
to, you know, they'd put their foot up
against the car, stick their hand on the
door handle, and just pull it. That's
the first reaction to do with a door
handle. When we went away with that and
we're starting to go now with normal
flush door handles, you have to you have
to start more drastic measures to open
the door. [music]
>> But there are signs that some of these
trends are finally reversing.
In March 2024, the European New Car
Assessment Program, or ENCAP, announced
big changes to its safety ratings.
[music] Beginning in 2026, cars won't be
able to earn a five-star rating unless
they contain physical switches for
specific functions. That includes the
horn, turn signals, hazard lights, and
windshield wipers. ENCAP isn't a
governmental body, but it's an
influential nonprofit backed by several
EU governments. Big car companies like
Volvo, BMW, and Tesla all advertise
their ENCAP safety ratings.
Many cars have essentially become phones
on wheels, and this appealed to some
drivers, at least in the showroom. But
then the rubber hit the road. In March
2024, What Car Magazine published a
survey of 1,428 drivers. It found that
almost 9 out of 10 preferred physical
controls to touchcreens. 60% even said
they'd be deterred from buying a new car
built around a touchcreen. This survey
is not a representative large-s scale
study, but it still raises a question.
If the new fangled features in so many
cars have potentially made roads less
safe and many drivers don't seem to like
them, are they truly innovations?
>> You know, it's just like, oh, come on.
So, that kind of is what I'm thinking.
Is this just a gimmick? Cuz gimmick
design is,
do you need it? Does it help you? That's
the first basic, you know, and does it
improve, you know, everything. In other
words, is a magic orb of emotional
connection really worth it? There's a
cost to these dubious innovations.
Literally, the affordable mid-pric car
seems to be going extinct, at least in
the US. In February 2025, the share of
new cars purchased costing less than
$25,000 was less than 5%, down more than
18% from just 6 years before. That's the
price range favored by many middle class
and first-time buyers. But there are
fewer of those on the market these days,
giving car companies an excuse to raise
prices on those that remain. and profit
margins are higher on tricked out
high-priced vehicles anyway. So many
dealers prioritize keeping those in
stock, not budget vehicles. If this
higher price point is more attractive
for sellers, could all these innovative
bells and whistles be another way of
nudging consumers in that direction? In
markets where large numbers of people
need to take out a loan to buy a car
like the US that's a serious issue. But
amid all the gloom and doom, there is
some good news. When Honda released its
2017 CRV, it made a change to the
infotainment system. The physical volume
knob was back, replacing what at least
one reviewer called an infuriating touch
slider.
BMW ditched gesture control, whereby
drivers could make flicking or spinning
gestures to control touchscreen
functions. But not many apparently
wanted to. And a year after NCIP rolled
out its new safety standards,
Volkswagen's head of design announced
that VW would be bringing back buttons
in all future models. Mint's comments
even seem to indicate a change in
mindset. We will never ever make this
mistake anymore. On the steering wheel,
we will have physical buttons. No
guessing anymore. There's feedback. It's
real and people love this. Honestly,
it's a car. It's not a phone. It's a
car. So, maybe automakers have learned
their lesson this time. Or maybe we'll
be asking the same questions in another
40 years. But the questions arise, is
the CRT really necessary? And is there a
built-in danger of looking away from the
road while you're trying to use it?